Alright so today's דף *Daf* is כ"א *Chof Aleph*. We pick up
in the middle of כ"ב עמוד ב' *Chof Amud Bais* and we
were dealing with רב אדא בר אבא Rav Adda bar Abba, *Rav
Adda bar Abba* who was this Rabbi who allowed people who were
accompanying him not to have to worry about falling buildings and falling
walls. He had this tremendous זכות zechus. *Zechus* and apparently we already
saw in one story that he wasn't even aware about how people
were שלעפינג *schlepping* him along and what was happening. And as we're
going to see now as the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* discusses what was
the source of his merit, it was about his complete involvement in
תורה Torah *Torah*. It sort of explains his being a little bit
oblivious. So let's take a look. It says like this: מאי הוה
עובדיה דרב אדא בר אבא *Mai hava ovdei d'Rav Adda bar Abba*?
כי הא דאיתמר *Ki ha d'itmar*. So the line starts with the
word איתמר *itmar*. It's about 20 lines from the bottom, right near
an asterisk, about five lines above where there's an asterisk and a
half
parenthesis. איתמר *itmar*, it was said. שאלו תלמידיו *Sha'alu talmidav*, his students
asked him, רב rav, אדא בר אבא *Rav Adda bar Abba*, במה
הארכת ימים *Bameh ha'arachta yamim*? In what merit did you live to
such an old age? אמר להם amar lahem, *Amar lahem*, he said
to them. So as opposed to before, it was about that he
saved people from falling buildings. Here it's to the question of old
age. What
did you do to merit such a long life? אמר להם amar
lahem *Amar lahem*, he said to them: מימי לא lo, הקפדתי בתוך
ביתי *Miyami lo hikpadeti betoch beiti*. In my entire life, I never
got upset about things in my house, which presumably
means to my wife or kids, but often has a context of
wife because I mean anybody, any of the members of the house.
ולא צעדתי בפני מי שגדול ממני *Velo tza'adti bifnei mi shegadol mimeni*.
I never took a step in front of somebody that was greater
than me. ולא הרהרתי במבואות המטונפות *Velo hirharti bemevo'ot hametunafot*. I did
not think תורה Torah, *Torah* in the filthy alleyways,
place inappropriate to be thinking תורה Torah, *Torah*, like not thinking תורה
Torah *Torah* in a toilet, in a bathroom. ולא הלכתי ד' אמות
בלא תורה Torah ובלא תפילין *Velo halachti daled amot belo Torah u'velo
tefillin*. But I never went four אמות *amot* without תורה Torah. *Torah*
and without תפילין *tefillin*. Maybe with the exception of when he went
through those alleyways. But okay. Anyway, but I was always wrapped up
physically and
literally and metaphorically in תורה Torah *Torah*. I was always and in
תפילין *tefillin*, because תפילין *tefillin* obviously represents תורה Torah. *Torah*. So I
was always with תורה Torah. *Torah* and תפילין *tefillin*. ולא ישנתי בבית
המדרש לא שינת קבע ולא שינת עראי *Velo yashanti be'veit hamedrash lo
shinat keva velo shinat arai*. I never went to sleep in the
בית המדרש Beit HaMidrash *Beit Hamedrash*, not a temporary and not a
long sleep. Let's see what's happening here. Excuse me a second. I
don't know what's going on here.
I'm sorry. Just one second. This thing is not... I don't know
what's going on here. Alright, anyway. So ולא ישנתי לא שינת קבע
ולא
שינת עראי *Velo yashanti lo shinat keva velo shinat arai*.
And so I never slept, meaning so I always both respected the
space of the בית המדרש *Beit Hamedrash* but also always involved in
my תורה Torah. *Torah*. ולא ששתי בתקלת חברי *Velo sashti betakalat chaveri*.
I was never rejoiced in the stumbling of my friend. There's a
German word for that, right? What's the word?
Schadenfreude. Right. So anyway, okay. ולא קראתי לחברי בחניכתו *Velo karati lachaveri
bechanichato*. ואמרי לה בחניכתו
*V'amri lah
bechanichato*. And I never called my friend in some type of a
כינוי *Kinuy*, a nickname. Two versions of a nickname. Some say it
means a nickname he gave himself and a nickname other people gave
him, or some people say it means a nickname other people gave
him, and חניכתו *Chanichato* might mean a family name, a last name,
that even though it was his name, it's not like a show
of respect, you know, you say,
"Hey, Linzer." So actually there's an interesting תוספות *Tosafot* on this. If
you look at תוספות *Tosafot* בחניכתו *bechanichato* says: פירש בכינוי שקורין אותו
בני אדם לגנאי *Peirush bekinuy shekorin oto bnei adam lignai*. That one
is a nickname, but a nickname that's used somewhat in a derogatory
sense. Raises an interesting question why it might not be derogatory but
it might not be fully respectful. Is there a גדר *geder* not
using it even if it's a non-derogatory nickname? And then the second
one תוספות *Tosafot* says: ובחניכתו *U'vechanichato*
excuse me פירש כינוי שם משפחתו *Peirush kinuy shem mishpachto*. שם לוואי
*Shem livai* like שם חניכת אבותיו *shem chanichat avotav* in גיטין *Gittin*
eighty-eight or eighty-five, דף פ"ח *daf pey chet*, דף פ"ה *daf pey
hey*, דוגמא *dugma* רבי אברהם Avraham אבן עזרא Ibn Ezra *Rabbi Avraham
Ibn Ezra*. So he wants to pick an example of a last
name. So what's the last name? You know, like the אבן עזרא
*Ibn Ezra*. שכל בני משפחתו היו נקראים כך *Shekol bnei mishpachto hayu
nikraim kach*. It wasn't that his father's name was Ezra. Everybody in
his family was אבן עזרא *Ibn Ezra*. That's the last name. ודוקא
לגנאי *V'davka lignai*. And that's only if it's done in a derogatory
way, like you say "Hey, אבן עזרא *Ibn Ezra*." So I don't
know, depends on who the person is, whether that's considered a proper
form of respect or whether that's a disrespectful form of respect. ולשבח
מותר *U'leshevach mutar*. If it's a respectful way, like we say the
אבן עזרא *Ibn Ezra* says, that's a respectful one. Anyway, it's fascinating
that he gives that as an example, but you know, the idea
of family names was I don't know the history of that, but
it's like it was not so prevalent in the time of תוספות
*Tosafot*. He needed to give an
illustration using
the
אבן עזרא *Ibn Ezra* as an illustration. Also fascinating. not somebody who
really is involved in גמרא, Gemara so it's fascinating. All right, so
now the גמרא Gemara continued.
So where are we? Okay, so that, so those things. Okay, so
anyway, not exactly clear to me, you know, it's a laundry list
of things, what the sort of common denominator of all those things
are. I mean obviously some of the things are there's overall an
issue of respect of not like and maybe in some ways it's
a little bit again of a critique of the earlier story, which
is also a self-critique about the rabbi that learned so much תורה
Torah, that he was so haughty, here's a person that's constantly learning
תורה, Torah. constantly involved in תורה, Torah but also, you know, he
knows his place, he doesn't step even one step in front of
somebody that is greater than him, he doesn't get upset at other
people, you know, he doesn't take upon himself the sense of like
entitlement to call other people by nicknames, gives everybody their full respect.
So I think it's a nice balance of the immersion in תורה
Torah, completely together with a sense of humility and treating people with
respect. So in that way at least it's a little bit of
a contrast to the earlier story. But other than that, you know,
it's hard to exactly know what to do with like this long
list of things. Yes.
אבן עזרא is a contemporary of בעלי תוספות. Ba'alei Tosafot.
That is correct.
Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara continues. Okay. אמר ליה רבא לרפרם
בר פפא לימא לן מר מהני מילי מעלייתא דהוה עביד רב הונא.
Amar leh Rava le-Rafram bar Pappa leima lan mar me-hanei milei ma'alyata
de-hava avid Rav Huna. Tell us some of the, רבא Rava said
to רפרם בר פפא, Rafram bar Pappa, tell us some of the
great things that רב הונא Rav Huna used to do. Since we're
talking about great things here that who was it here did, רב
rav. אדא בר אבא, so now let's do another types of lists
of great deeds of
rabbi. אמר ליה באנקותיה לא דכירנא. Amar leh be-ankusei lo dechirna. I
don't remember things he did in his youth. בסיבותיה דכירנא, be-seivutei dechirna,
in his older age I remember. דכל יומא דעיבא, De-chol yoma de-eiva,
every day that it was cloudy, הוו מפקי ליה בגוהרקי דדהבא, havu
mafki leh be-guharkei de-dahava, they brought him out in a gold like
throne, or not throne but like some type of thing like a
seat that you carry, you know, you carry somebody on.
So first of all that's already, you know, your eyebrows are going
up, like gold, a gold throne that they bring him out, a
gold seat, like sounds a little haughty, but let's see what he
would do.
וסייר ליה לכולה מתא, Ve-sayer leh le-chulah mata, he would go ahead
and he would inspect the entire city. וכל אשישתא דהויא רעיעתא, Ve-chol
ashista de-hava rei'ata, every wall that was shaky, going back to the
theme of shaky
walls, הוה סתר לה, hava satar lah, he would demolish it.
אי אפשר למר בני לה, Ei efshar le-mar benei lah, if the
owners had the means, then the owners would have to rebuild it
on their own because their wall was representing a threat to people
and it was their responsibility. ואי לא אפשר, Ve-i lo efshar, and
if they didn't have the means, בני לה איהו מדידיה, benei lah
ihu mi-dideih, he would rebuild it on his own fund, with his
own funds. ובכל פניא דמעלי שבתא, U-ve-chol panya de-ma'alei shabbata, every ערב
שבת, erev Shabbat, הוה משדר שלוחא לשוקא, hava meshader shlucha le-shuka, he
would send a messenger to the שוק, shuk, to the marketplace. וכל
ירקא דהוה פייש להו לגינאי, Ve-chol yarka de-hava payish lehu le-ginai, and
any vegetables, any food that was left over late Friday afternoon that
would obviously get thrown out because they couldn't be refrigerated, זבין ליה,
zavin leh, he would buy them up, ושדי ליה לנהרא, ve-shadi leh
le-nahara, and he would throw them into the river. He had no
use for them but he would buy them up, and we'll see
the reason he would buy them up is in order to encourage
the sellers to bring all of their wares, you know,
to the marketplace so people would have enough and they would have
a full range of
options and they shouldn't worry that it'll all go to waste.
Agricultural price support. There you go. Although that's in terms of growing
the food, here it's in terms of encouraging it
all to be brought to the market. But okay. וליתיב לעניים, Ve-liteiv
le-aniyim, so the גמרא Gemara says one minute, there's a question that
comes up nowadays, you know, the stuff that restaurants throw out, why
don't you just give it to the poor, why are you throwing
it out? So the גמרא Gemara says no, זימנין דסמכא דעתייהו ולא
אתו למיזבן. zimnin de-samcha da'atayhu ve-lo atu le-mizban. No,
because then what will happen is that people will assume oh, he's
going to, why do we have to buy food for
שבת, Shabbat, רב הונא Rav Huna will just buy it all up
and give it to us. So therefore and they won't buy. Now
why would that be a bad thing? So fine, let him do
that. So רש״י Rashi here says, what does רש״י Rashi say? דניסמכו
אהני ובלי לא אתו למיזבן פירוש איננו צריכים לקנות De-nisamchu ahanei u-ve-li
lo atu le-mizban peirush einenu tzrichim liknot ושמא לא יישאר שם כלום
ואין להם
מה לאכול בשבת, ve-shema lo yisha'er sham klum ve-ein lahem mah le-echol
be-Shabbat, that if they wait till the end and he buys up
only the stuff at the end, then maybe there won't be anything
left over and then they won't have what to and they won't
have, you know, any food for שבת. Shabbat. So he didn't want
to have them overly rely on that.
Okay, one minute. So where are we? Okay. ולישדייה לבהמה, Ve-lishdyeih le-behemah,
so fine, but at least give it to animals. קסבר מאכל אדם
אין מאכילין לבהמה *Kasavar ma'achal adam ein ma'achilin livheima*. No you don't
feed human food to animals, which is quite funny because presumably the
reason is you don't want to waste the food, but here it's
going to waste anyway. Somehow it's seen as more disrespectful to the
food to feed it to animals, you know, maybe it more is,
you know, seeming like a—I don't know—dehumanizing to people that you feed
human food to animals and that's somehow seen as more of a
problem than just throwing it out. Yes.
We're supposed to feed טרף *treif* meat to dogs.
Yeah,
okay, but that's a question about what your purview of human consumption
is, you know, if you're within, you know, if you're talking about,
you know, we the people who would eat it, if your extensive
community is the Jewish people, so I think that that—but you know,
but the Torah also says that you sell it, like לגר אשר
בשעריך תתננה או מכור לנכרי *l'ger asher b'isharecha titnena o machor l'nochri*.
You know, so anyway, there are different—דווקא *davka* the פסוקים pesukim *psukim*
in the Torah is also mentioning giving it to the non-Jews in
that case. Anyway, okay. ולא יזבני כלל *v'lo yizbeney klal*, so why
is he bothering to buy it? No, נמצאת מכשילן לעתיד לבוא *nimtzas
machshilan l'atid lavo*, then he's going to cause them, the sellers, to
stumble because then they will—or you know, it'll, you know, they'll—I mean,
not stumble, but it'll be hurtful to the economy, to the people,
because then they won't bring all of their food to the market.
So it's quite an interesting story, you know, on the one hand,
he's going out with his gold chair, which, you know, he sort
of—which represents a little ostentatiousness of his wealth, you know, you wonder
what that's about, you know, but on the other hand, it's like
okay, you know, maybe he—here's somebody that, you know, does have this
sort of sense of כבוד *kavod* for himself, but at the same
time, you know, he's very much—you know, concerned about the community well-being.
And again, you know, again maybe I'm overreading into all of these
stories, but here you have these stories about great people, and to
me it seems that it's all somewhat in the background of the
חוני *Choni* stories. So חוני *Choni* on the one hand didn't go
out in any gold chair, you know, they had to go find
out חוני *Choni*, he was who knows where he was, but חוני
*Choni* wasn't—wasn't also concerned about public welfare, right? He wasn't the one
that was concerned that nobody was getting rain. Here's somebody that is
very proactively, on the one hand, taking a certain amount of כבוד
*kavod* to himself, you know, sort of like, it's a wonderful thing,
take all the כבוד *kavod* you want, just you know, as long
as you're serving the community and you're helping us out, you know,
if it's important for you to get that כבוד *kavod*, געזונטערהייט *gezunterheit*.
So that I think is an interesting contrast that he's דווקא *davka*
has—is taking the כבוד *kavod*, but on the other hand, a type
of, you know, of proactive and, you know, out of his own
funds and his own efforts taking in the communal concerns. What's exactly
to do with the fact that it's better to throw it out
than to give to animals or to give to the poor, you
know, raises I think interesting questions.
And these other חכמים *hachamim* are not miracle workers.
And they're not miracle workers, right. They're doing it all in very
practical ways.
There's almost a low-key allure in this—this—this story.
Exactly. I think it's consistently setting up counter-חוני *Choni* models. And it's
exactly that. Right. And they're working very much in a very real-world
type of a way in this—in this.
Yeah, Porphy, בן יהוידע
*Ben Yehoyada*, it says he deliberately went in the gold chair because
he went into the non-Jewish neighborhoods and it gave him street cred
or he was credible because they—because he was such a wealthy man
and if he was doing good things, they would follow his lead
and help him out.
Ah, okay, that's a nice explanation.
And there's another פשט *pshat* that says it's pitting out his rod.
All right, and on that note, okay. כי הוי ליה מילתא דאסותא
*ki hava leh milsa d'asuta*, okay,
now, when he would have a—when he would have some type of
a remedy, some type of a—for—for disease, some type of a medicine,
הוה מלי כוזא דמיא *hava malei kuza d'maya* or הוה מלי כוזא
*hava malei kuza*, he would fill up some type of a container,
וטלי ליה בסיפא דדשא *v'taley lei b'sifa d'dasha*, and he would hang
it like at, you know, outside of his house, ואמר כל דצריך
ליתי ולישקול *v'amar kol d'tzarich l'eisei v'lishkol*, anybody who needs this medicine
can come and take. ואיכא דאמרי *v'ika d'amrei*, and that—A—would provide it
for the community and B would allow people, you know, privacy. You
wouldn't have to announce the fact that you were sick or that
you needed the medicine or go even to him directly. You could
go ahead and just take it on your own and nobody was
looking. ואיכא דאמרי *v'ika d'amrei*, and some say, מילתא דשיבתא *milsa d'shivsa*,
he knew the—the matters relating to שיבתא *shivsa*, which is a certain
like a shade—which was the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says happens when you don't wash your hands, this
evil spirit comes into you. והוה מנח כוזא דמיא *hava manach kuza
d'maya*, and he would fill—so here with more about just again talking
about public well-being, trying to address issues of public health. So he
would fill up a vessel of water, ודלי ליה *v'dalei lei*, and
like fill it up, ואמר כל דצריך ליתי וליעל *v'amar kol d'tzarich
l'eisei v'liel*, anybody who needs—should come—you know, doesn't have running water or
needs water should come and wash their hands with this, דלא ליסתכן
*d'lo l'istakein*, that they should not be endangered. So here in a
way it's very nice, it's sort of like the previous thing. It's,
you know, it's something like he's concerned about public health issues and
trying to do things. So we had price support, so whatever, we
had supports of merchants, and here we have public health. כי הוה
כריך ריפתא *ki hava karich rifta*, when he would eat bread—literally wrap
bread, but it means when he would break bread, when he would
eat—הוה פתח לבביה livaveih, *hava patach l'vaveih*, he would like open up
his heart, ואמר כל מן דצריך ליתי וליכול *v'amar kol man d'tzarich
l'eisei v'lechol*. like a like a פסח, right? Like the סדר. Seder.
Anybody who needs should come and eat. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so
רבא Rava said,
where was I? כלהו מצינא מקיימנא, kuleihu matzinan mekaymi, I can do
all of this, I could live up to all of his examples,
I wonder if רבא Rava had to had the money to live
up to it, but presumably he felt he could. לבר מהא, Livar
meiha, except for that last one, that just opening up your doors
to everyone.
דלא מצינא למעבד, d'lo matzina l'me'avad, that I can't do, why?
משום דנפישי בני מחוזא, mishum d'nafishei benei Mechuza, because there's too many
the-מחוזא. Mechuza. Either there's too many troops in מחוזא Mechuza or just
have the phrase בני מחוזא, benei Mechuza, there are too many people
in מחוזא Mechuza and I could not open up my doors to
everyone. I think I read that the word wrong there, it wasn't
לבביה, it's לבוביה levaveih to his doors? He would open up his
gates like בבא, bava, I'm sorry about that, he would open up
his doors anyway and call anybody who wants. So anyway רבא Rava
says I could do any of that except for except for the
except for the last one. That's just I'd be overrun.
Is this still רב אדא בר אהבה? Rav Adda bar Ahava? Yes.
I mean by רב הונא. Rav Huna. רב הונא. Rav Huna. Yes,
this is רב הונא, Rav Huna, right, רב הונא. Rav Huna. Okay.
Top of כ"ה עמוד א'. Kaf Heh Amud Aleph. יופי רב יוחנן,
Yofi Rav Yochanan, very famous story now. Okay so that was, okay
so that was about again people of great merit and also particularly
also about their you know the one case was just learning תורה
Torah and respecting people. The other case
was it's right in contrast to the whole story about the person
who said how ugly you are and his haughtiness. But this last
story was great people in terms of what they do for the
community. Let's take a look now at this story.
אלפא ורב יוחנן Ilfa v'Rav Yochanan on a slightly different theme. אלפא
ורב יוחנן הוו גרסי באורייתא. Ilfa v'Rav Yochanan havah garsi b'Oraisa. They
were learning תורה. Torah דחיקא להו מילתא, Dachika lehu milta, but there
was a, they were having a real hard time financially, טובא, tuva,
exceedingly so. אמרו Amru and they said, ניקום וניזיל ונעביד עיסקא. neikum
v'neizil v'na'avid iska. You know what, maybe we should set aside the
learning and go into business, we have to start earning some money.
ונקיים בנפשין U'nekayeim b'nafshein and we should fulfill in ourselves the verse,
אפס כי לא יהיה בך אביון, Efess ki lo yihyeh becha evyon,
there should be no poor among you. So לא יהיה בך, lo
yihyeh becha, you yourself shouldn't be poor, you have a responsibility to
make sure that you're not poor. So you have a responsibility to
support yourself. אזלו, Azlu, אותבי תותי גודא. osevi tusei guda. So they
went and they were on going wherever you left the בית מדרש
Beis Medrash were on their journey to start seeking out a פרנסה.
parnassah. And they were sitting underneath a bridge. רעיא, re'iya, again a
shaky bridge. Again notice the theme of shaky walls, shaky buildings. I
he knocked down shaky walls, they're underneath a shaky bridge. And and
again what we've heard before about the shaky wall was that they
wouldn't whoever it was רב ושמואל Rav u'Shmuel I think it was,
was it רב ושמואל Rav u'Shmuel wouldn't walk by the shaky wall
they were afraid it would fall but they had רב אדא בר
אהבה Rav Adda bar Ahava there or רב I'm forgetting who we're
talking about רב אדא בר אהבה, Rav Adda bar Ahava, his merit
prevented the wall from falling. So that's like the background here. They're
under a shaky bridge, we already know what could happen if you're
under a shaky wall shaky bridge if you don't have sufficient merit.
Okay so they were under this shaky bridge. הוו קא כרכי ריפתא,
havah ka karchi rifta, they were breaking bread, eating bread. אתו תרי
מלאכי השרת, asu terei malachei hashareis, two heavenly angels came. שמע רב
יוחנן, shama Rav Yochanan, and רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan overheard the heavenly
angels talking to one another and one said to the other, נישדי
עלייהו, nishdi aleihu,
let's cast this bridge bridge on them, האי גודא ונקטלינהו, hai guda
v'niktlineihu, and let's kill them. Why? שמניחים חיי עולם ועוסקים בחיי שעה
shemanichim chayei olam v'oskim b'chayei sha'ah
because they've abandoned eternal life they've abandoned the learning of תורה and
involving themselves in this worldly life in in making money so they
did such a terrible thing let's cast the bridge on them. So
אמר ליה אידך, amar lei idach, the other one said back, שבקינהו,
shavkeinu, no, leave them alone. דאיכא בהו חד, d'ika behu chad, there's
one of them, one of those two, דקיימא ליה שעתא, d'kaima lei
sha'ata, that literally like the the time is standing for him meaning
that he's going to be very you know that he's going to
raise to great heights. So and he doesn't deserve to die. רב
יוחנן שמע, Rav Yochanan shama, now רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan heard this
conversation. אלפא לא שמע, Ilfa lo shama, אלפא Ilfa didn't hear the
conversation. אמר ליה רב יוחנן לאלפא, Amar lei Rav Yochanan l'Ilfa, so
רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan said to אלפא Ilfa who wasn't aware whether
אלפא Ilfa had heard or not, שמע מר מידי? shama mar midi?
Have you did you hear anything? אמר ליה, Amar lei, לא, no.
So rather than saying so I must be hearing things and going
crazy he said no he said אמר, amar, מדשמעי אנא mi'desham'ei ana
that I heard this ואלפא לא שמע v'Ilfa lo shama and אלפא
Ilfa didn't hear it, שמע מינה לדידי קיימא לי שעתא. shma mina
l'didi kaima li sha'ata. So obviously they must be talking about me
because I'm at a level that I was able to hear this.
So it must be that my time has come in terms of
like the world of תורה. So אמר ליה רב יוחנן, amar lei
Rav Yochanan, so רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan said to him אהדר, ahadar,
I'm going to go back to the בית מדרש. Beis Medrash. ואוקי
בנפשאי v'okei b'nafshai
and I'll fulfill in my verse rather the verse make sure you're
not poor I'm going to fulfill in my by myself the verse
כי לא יחדל אביון מקרב הארץ, ki lo yechdal evyon mikerev ha'aretz,
there's never not going to be poor. So I'll be one of
the poor. So okay there's got to be poor let it be
me. I'm going to go back and learn תורה. רב יוחנן הדר,
Rav Yochanan hadar, רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan went back. אלפא לא הדר,
Ilfa lo hadar, אלפא Ilfa didn't go back. עד דאתא
אלפא ad d'ata Ilfa until אלפא Ilfa returned returned from his going
out into the wide world and making his fortune, so we're talking
we could be talking about many years later so But in the
interim, אמליך רבי יוחנן, amlikh Rabbi Yochanan, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan had
literally become king, but it means רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan had been
appointed as the ראש ישיבה. Rosh Yeshiva. And as רש''י Rashi points
out, that does not just mean a position of status, but also
presumably
he was given,
he was given significant,
whatever, he was given funds, wealth, in order to, you know, give
status to his position. So look at the רש''י, Rashi, the third
line, the narrow line, מלכו של רבי יוחנן Malkhu shel Rabbi Yohanan
means מינוהו ראש ישיבה. Minuhu Rosh Yeshiva. ועינו מנהג, Ve-eynu minhag, מי
שהיה ראש ישיבה mi she-haya Rosh Yeshiva היו מגדלין אותו משלהן hayu
migadlin oto mi-she-lahen ומעשירין אותו. u-ma'ashirin oto. So if the person was
not independently wealthy, they would help,
you know, give him money in order to make him wealthy. כדאמרן
לגבי כהן גדול K'd'amran le-gabei Kohen Gadol בספרא וביומא, be-Sifra u-ve-Yoma, והכהן
הגדול מאחיו, ve-ha-Kohen ha-Gadol mei-echav, גדלהו משל אחיו. gadleihu mi-shel echav. So
I'm not sure if that's also clear in the פסוקים that it
means like, oh, not only did he get to be a ראש
ישיבה, Rosh Yeshiva, he also got to be, you know, to have
his issues of poverty addressed, but nevertheless there is that sense that,
you know, that the poverty issue was no longer a concern of
his. They gave him a desk.
They gave him a desk, exactly, and an office. Okay. So now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. אמרו לו, Amru lo, they
said to him, אי אותיב מר וגריס ei otiv Mar ve-garis לא
הוי מליך מר. lo havei malikh Mar. So they said to, what's
his name, they said to אילפא, Ilfa, if the master, if the
master, meaning if you, אילפא, Ilfa, had stayed in the בית מדרש
Beit Midrash and learned, then the other master, רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan,
wouldn't have been the ראש ישיבה. Rosh Yeshiva. You would have been
the ראש ישיבה. Rosh Yeshiva. You were smarter than רבי יוחנן. Rabbi
Yochanan. You knew more than רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. If you had
just stayed in the בית מדרש, Beit Midrash, it would have been
you, not him. It must have made him feel real good. So
what did he do?
אזל תלי נפשיה
באסקריא דספינתא.
Azal tali
nafshia be-askarya de-sefunta.
So he went and he suspended himself from the mast of the
boat. The mast is the big pole in the middle. That's the
mast, right? Okay. From the mast of the boat. אמר, Amar, he
said, אי איכא דשאיל לי במתניתא דרבי חייא ורבי אושעיא. Ei ika
de-sha'il li be-matnita de-Rabbi Hiyya ve-Rabbi Oshaya. I'm going to show you
how much I know. If anybody can ask me anything
on any of the ברייתות braitot of רבי חייא ורבי אושעיא, Rabbi
Hiyya ve-Rabbi Oshaya, they were the ones who, like, you know, who
edited the ברייתות braitot and the תוספתא. Tosefta. דלא פשטינא ליה ממתניתין.
De-lo pashitna lei mi-matnitin.
And I cannot prove to you that that's already anchored, rooted in
a משנה. Mishnah. So then, נפילנא מאסקריא דספינתא וטבענא. nafilna mi-askarya de-sefunta
ve-tavana.
I'll cast myself from the mast of the boat and I'll drown
myself. Okay, it's a little,
a little dramatic, exactly. But anyway, I'm going to prove how masterful
is my knowledge. Not only do I know the משנה Mishnah and
the ברייתא, braita, I'll be able to show you how they're all
connected. Okay. אתו. Atu. So someone took him up on his, you
know, on his offer, on his challenge. תנא ליה, Tana lei, and
taught him the following ברייתא. braita. האומר תנו שקל לבני בשבת. Ha-omer
tenu shekel le-vanai be-shabbat. Somebody basically is about to pass away and
he's leaving,
you know, a,
you know, a fund. Yeah, but what do you call it when
you set, not just a fund, a trust. Right, a trust for
his kids. So he says, here's the money, and what I want
you to do is provide for my children one שקל shekel each
week out of this trust. והם ראויים לתת להם סלע. Ve-hem re'uyim
latet lahem sela. The only thing is that there's so many kids
and just to provide reasonably for their needs, they deserve a סלע,
sela, more than a שקל. shekel. So what do you do? נותנים
להם סלע. Notnim lahem sela. You can give them what they need.
Now why, why isn't that violating what he said? Well, one way
of understanding that is because, you know, it's the principle of יש
בכלל מאתיים מנה. yesh bi-khlal matayim maneh. If he said give them
a hundred, he didn't say give them only a hundred, so give
them two hundred. Two hundred is also a hundred. It's there. So
then that you're allowed to do. ואם אמר אל תתנו להם אלא
שקל. Ve-im amar al titnu lahem ela shekel. If he said, "Don't
give them but a שקל," shekel, don't give them more than that,
אין נותנים להם אלא שקל. ein notnim lahem ela shekel. Then you
can only give them a שקל, shekel, you can't give them more.
Now, אם אמר, im amar, now if he said, give them a
hundred, not only a hundred, give them a hundred a week. But
then he also added to that, מתו ירשו אחרים תחתיהם. metu yirshu
acherim tachtechem. If they die, then some other people, not their children,
should be the next, you know,
inheritors of the fund, should be the next beneficiaries of the fund
if they die. So in that case, all the money isn't coming
to the kids, right? Because it's not that it then passes on
to the kids' kids. It goes to some other party. So in
that case, בין שאמר תנו בין שאמר אל תתנו, bein she-amar tenu
bein she-amar al titnu, whether he says give them, whether he says
don't give them, in either case, אין נותנים להם אלא שקל. ein
notnim lahem ela shekel. You don't give them more than a hundred
because clearly this money is not all going to them. Whatever is
left over is going to someone else. So therefore you don't have
the same degree of latitude of interpreting what he said, a hundred,
he didn't say no more than a hundred, we'll give them two.
No, you assume that he meant precisely in that case because he's
intending that other people will ultimately be the beneficiaries. It's not like
all the money is eventually going to go to them anyway. So
anyway, so who is, so that's a ברייתא. braita. Very interesting. How
is it tied into a משנה? Mishnah? אמר ליה, Amar lei, he
said to him,
הא מני רבי מאיר היא. Ha mani Rabbi Meir hi. רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir who says it's a מצוה mitzvah to do what the
מת met says, so this ברייתא's Baraita working out what exactly are
the parameters of interpreting what it was that he said when he
says 100. Does he mean exactly 100? Does he mean no less
than 100? Does it depend on other things he said, how he
interprets that word? But all of that is figuring out how to
interpret within a context and within what the other types of needs
are, what it is that he said, but assumes as a basis
that you have to do what the מת's met commanded. And there's
a, you know, it's not like he gave this over as a
מתנה. matanah. This is actually he gave this over as a ציווי.
tzivuy. He said this is my deathbed wish that I want you
to distribute the funds this way, right? So that's a principle, I
mean when we get to בבא בתרא Bava Batra we'll learn there
are two ways in which somebody can distribute their funds other than
allow natural inheritance to take place. One is a deathbed bequest, you
know, which actually is like a will, and the other is that
you're not actually transferring the ownership of it, but you're giving a
ציווי. tzivuy. You're saying here's, you know, here's how I want you
to treat the funds, but it's not an actual transfer of the
funds. And that's this issue of מצוה לקיים דברי המת. mitzvah lekayem
divrei hamet. So he said this is all based on a position
we have in a משנה Mishna of מצוה לקיים דברי המת mitzvah
lekayem divrei hamet and this is a ברייתא Baraita just working out
the parameters of how to interpret what it is that he's actually
saying and how that actually should be interpreted in the particular context.
All right, so that did not seem so, I mean it's interesting,
you know, because it's not like the exact point is in the
משנה, Mishna, right? There's obviously much more of a working out of
a very general principle in the משנה, Mishna, but he's saying nevertheless
I have all of the information of all the ברייתות. Baraitot. Not
only do I know it, but I have it organized so I
can sort of locate it in the various משניות Mishnayot and tell
you the ברייתות Baraitot here are working out the implications of this
משנה, Mishna, you know, this ברייתא Baraita is working out the implications
of that משנה. Mishna. And the point I think being that not
only did he have mastery of the material, but he had it
all sort of very, you know, well-organized and sort of and sort
of associated with one another. So that shows, you know, his mastery
of תורה. Of course it's not exactly an analytic ability, okay, but
it's also not the other extreme which is just like, you know,
the גמרא Gemara sometimes talks about סיני Sinai like somebody who just
knows all the information but sometimes there's like a derogatory phrase of
like, you know, he's like a
חמור נושא ספרים. chamor nosei sefarim. He's like a donkey laden with
books. Like okay, he just knows a lot of information. So on
the one hand, you don't see demonstrated here tremendous analytic ability, but
what you do see is, you know, the mastery of like what
he's demonstrating is the mastery of all of the knowledge but in
a way that's organized and linked and makes sense and categorized and
so on.
Yeah, just as accurate as it's interesting it seems to me that
he doesn't, they obviously he doesn't refer to these teachings as ברייתות
Baraitot or as תוספתא, Tosefta, it's their משנה Mishna and our משנה.
Mishna.
Yeah, but I
think the משנה Mishna of רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya and אושעיא Oshaya
as opposed to מתניתין matnitin our משנה. Mishna.
You're right, that is very right. I translated it as ברייתא Baraita
but you're right, that is the way it is phrased, their משנה,
Mishna, our משנה, Mishna, and מתניתין matnisin is always our משנה, Mishna,
that is correct.
But sounds like there was some level playing field.
Yeah, but I don't think so. I think that the very statement
there's always that assumption like our, you know, means means the canonical,
the authoritative one.
You're right, that is the phrase, but the fact that he's linking
it in our משנה Mishna if anything could be shown to be
doing the opposite point basically saying that all of this, you know,
our משנה Mishna is, you know, is authoritative, is canonical, everything else
sort of is a commentary on it or as a derivation of
it. But yeah, I think I don't think in anywhere in the
גמרא Gemara do you get a sense that ברייתא Baraita and משנה
Mishna are on an equal playing field. Yeah, interesting thing here is
one
more thing as opposed to the moral of the story.
Right,
exactly. The only common thing is the bridge and the shaky bridge
or whatever, but
in terms of the context maybe because a lot of these stories
have to do with miracle workers or חסידים Chassidim or whatever who
like אילפא, Ilfa, you know, he didn't just stay in the בית
מדרש, Beit Midrash, he was involved with the community,
פרנסה, Parnasa, you know, he obviously
maybe אילפא's Ilfa trying to say it would be very nice to
be ראש ישיבה Rosh Yeshiva but this can also be, it can
also be,
it's interesting because I was reading this that it's like אילפא's Ilfa
making a spectacle of himself, you know, it's not like what he
does is so amazing, and even if he did amazing, it's like
okay, but now instead of being a ראש ישיבה Rosh Yeshiva you're
a guy on a mast of a boat, you know. So if
anything I sort of saw this in the opposite way, which was
like we're talking about the power of going out and taking care
of the needs of the community, you know, but אילפא's Ilfa just
going and like, you know, and taking care of his own, you
know, right now it's not like he wanted to be rich necessarily,
he didn't want to be poor, but you know, but I think
the point of this is exactly sort of speak about
the choosing between like a life of תורה, you know, and a
life of business or of making money, and it's really coming to
sort of, really the critique is on seems to be clearly that
it's
on אילפא. Ilfa. That's the way I see it and that like
okay we've been talking about the importance of using your funds and
taking care of the needs of the community, you know, but that
doesn't but that shouldn't be led to say so I'll just go
into business and not learn תורה. I mean, that's the way I
read it. Yeah.
So just to drill down on this a little further, the question
is
because and the question that starts the prologue of our story is
that you've
got these two ישיבה Yeshiva בחורים bochers
who go into business.
Right. And the story is about theirs who can survive. Ah, that's
nice. Uh-huh. Of what's happening here.
And maybe that story is supposed to be some reference
to רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
who goes back to the ישיבה Yeshiva and is actually getting taken
care of as you pointed out before. It seems like they're going
above and beyond providing. It makes the question really did allow what's
supposed to be about the use of the endowment beyond minimal support.
And אילפא Ilfa doesn't get it. So he answers off, I'm not
sure exactly where to go with it but there seems...
Yeah, that's a very nice point, that like there's a limited amount
of funds and what do you do? Do you try to sort
of stretch the funds, which is the first case of the ברייתא,
Braita, you read the words in a way to type stretch the
funds? Or do you accept sort of the דברי המת divrei hamet
and you limit yourself to the funds and you figure out how
to make do, you know? And, you know, it's sort of like,
I mean, like יירשו אחרים תחתיהם, yeirshu acherim tachteihem, means for other
people to get the money. That's what יוחנן Yochanan said, I'll be
poor, other people will get the money, it'll all work out in
the end, you know, but I'm not going to try to stretch
the funds. I'll stay within those realities and work with it. That's
a brilliant idea. That's very nice. שקויח. Shkoyach. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמרו עליו. Amru alav.
So where were we? אמרו עליו על נחום איש גמזו. Amru alav
al Nachum Ish Gamzu. So this now we get to some נחום
איש גמזו Nachum Ish Gamzu stories, we can try to figure out
how it's connected, but let's take a look. They said about נחום
איש גמזו Nachum Ish Gamzu שהיה סומא משתי עיניו, shehaya suma mishtei
einav,
was blind in his two eyes, גידם משתי ידיו, gidem mishtei yadav,
he was had the I don't know what the word for it
is, but he he didn't have either either of his arms, קיטע
משתי רגליו, kiteia mishtei raglav, he didn't have his two legs, they
were both cut off, וכל גופו מלא שחין, vechol gufo malei shechin,
his whole torso was filled with blisters, you know, and sores, והיה
מוטל בבית רעוע, vehaya mutal beveit ra'ua, he was at the one
obvious link, he was in the again the shaky house, we had
a shaky wall, a shaky bridge, a shaky house, ורגלי מטתו מונחים
בספלים של מים, veraglei mitato munachim besefalim shel mayim,
and the legs of the bed were in buckets of water כדי
שלא יעלו עליו נמלים kdei shelo ya'alu alav nemalim so that like
weasels should not climb the bed because he didn't have any arms
or limbs to push them off, so the buckets of water, what?
Ants, I'm sorry, right, ants, so that he didn't have any he
didn't have any limbs to push them off. פעם אחת הייתה מטתו
מונחת בבית רעוע, pa'am achat hayta mitato munachat beveit ra'ua, we're back
to the shaky house, so his bed was in a shaky house.
ביקשו תלמידיו לפנות מטתו, bikshu talmidav lifnot mitato, they wanted to get
his bed out so the house wouldn't fall down on him like
the previous story, right, when he wanted to get the wine out,
you know, out of the shaky house, ואחר כך לפנות את הכלים,
ve'achar kach lifnot et hakelim, and then to worry about getting out
all of the other like, you know, vessels. אמר להם, he said
to them, בני, פנו את הכלים ואחר כך פנו את מטתי, banai,
panu et hakelim ve'achar kach panu et mitati, first take out the
vessels and then take me out, שמובטח לכם shemuvtach lachem שכל זמן
שאני בבית אין הבית נופל, shekol zman she'ani babayit ein habayit nofel,
as long as I'm in the house
it would not fall down. So mamash this is the real parallel
to the previous story with רב אדא בר אהבה, his תורה protected
him and he wasn't even aware. Here נחום איש גמזו Nachum Ish
Gamzu is quite aware that he is being protected. Of course the
irony is the house isn't falling down, but look at what terrible
things have already happened to him. So we're going to look at
that. But anyway, so what did they do? פנו את הכלים ואחר
כך פנו את מטתו ונפל הבית. pinu et hakelim ve'achar kach pinu
et mitato venafal habayit. So fine, they followed his instruction, first they
took out the vessels, then they took him out, then the house
fell down. Mamash a parallel to the earlier story. Okay, אמרו לו
תלמידיו, amru lo talmidav, so his students said to him, so that
at least presumably is the reason this is being brought in about
shaky houses. But now that we're talking about him, אמרו לו תלמידיו,
amru lo talmidav, his student said to him, רבי, וכי מאחר שצדיק
גמור אתה, Rebbi, vechi me'achar shetzadik gamur ata, Rabbi, since you're so
righteous that you protected the house from falling down, למה עלתה לך
כך, lama alta lecha kach, how could this terrible things happen to
you about what has happened to your body? אמר להם בני, amar
lahem banai, he said my children, אני גרמתי לעצמי, ani garamti le'atzmi,
I brought it upon myself. שפעם אחת הייתי מהלך בדרך לבית חמי,
shepa'am achat hayiti mehalekh baderekh leveit chami,
once I was going on the way to my father-in-law's house, והיה
עמי משוי ג' חמורים, vehaya imi masui gimel chamorim, and I was
carrying with me the load of three donkeys, אחד של מאכל, echad
shel ma'achal, one of food, אחד של משתה, echad shel mishteh, one
of drink, ואחד של מיני מגדים, ve'echad shel minei megadim, and the
other of all types of delicacies. So, בא עני אחד, ba ani
echad,
a poor person came, so to me this is evoking that earlier
story, right, with who was it with? Who said like, you know,
who was coming from the בית המדרש and, you know, he was
traveling on the river and he said, you know, and the person
came who was ugly and disgusting, so here he was anyway also
a little bit. evokes אליעזר, Eliezer, you know going to the future
or עבד אברהם Eved Avraham the future father-in-law's house laden down with
all these good things. Anyway so a certain poor person came to
me ועמד לי בדרך ואמר לי רבי פרנסני ve-amad li ba-derech ve-amar
li Rabbi parneseni and he said to me, my master, support me,
feed me. אמרתי לו amarti lo I said to him, המתן עד
שאפרוק מן החמור hamten ad she-efrok min ha-chamor give me a second
so I can unladen it from the donkey. I have these bundles
of food, let me untie some of the bundles and give you
the food. ולא הספקתי לפרוק מן החמור ve-lo hispakti lifrok min ha-chamor
I did not have a chance to undo it from the donkey,
undo the burden from the donkey, עד שיצתה נשמתו ad she-yatzata nishmato
he died from hunger. הלכתי ונפלתי על פניו halachti ve-nafalti al panav
I went and I fell on his face ואמרתי ve-amarti and I
said, עיני שלא חסו על עיניך einai she-lo chasu al einecha my
eyes that did not have compassion on your eyes, יסומו yasumu should
be made blind. ידי שלא חסו על ידיך yadai she-lo chasu al
yadecha my hands that did not have compassion on your hands, יתגדמו
yitgadmu should be cut off. רגלי שלא חסו על רגליך raglai she-lo
chasu al raglecha my legs that did not have compassion on your
legs, יתקטעו yitkate’u should be cut off. ולא נתקררה דעתי ve-lo nitkarrera
da'ati and I still did not feel calmed עד שאמרתי ad she-amarti
until I said, כל גופי יהיה מלא שחין kol gufi yihiye malei
shechin let my whole body be filled with boils. אמרו לו amru
lo they said to him, אוי לנו שראינוך בכך oy lanu she-re'inucha
be-kach woe to us that we've seen you in such a state,
so completely, you know, disfigured. אמר להם he said to them, אוי
לי אם לא ראיתוני בכך oy li im lo re'ituni be-kach woe
to me if you had not seen me like this because then
I would not have been properly punished for what I did wrong.
So I have to tell you I don't understand this story. I
mean, what did he do wrong? He had to get his stuff
out of the package. Like, his stuff was in the package. Are
we supposed to assume that he had food more readily available? Like,
his lunch. I could have given him my lunch, I wanted to
give him some of the other food, not the food I was
in the middle of eating. I mean, if that's true, it doesn't
say it here. Was he a little bit slow in undoing the
package? He's just gonna plop. Right, maybe that... but even if that's
part of the critique, that you should have been able to see
how he was starving to death, like what are you supposed to
do if your stuff's all in your luggage? So you have to
assume other things, like he had more readily available food. So number
one, it's not so clear what he did wrong. Number two, you
know, his reaction seems like way over the top and you know,
and also like in a way that is... on the one hand
like learning מסכת תענית Masechet Ta'anit it's worth thinking about the idea
of like self, like punishing the body as a way of atoning.
Now in our מסכת masechet as I've been trying to point out,
the theme of atonement has not really been there,
you know, I would say like there was one place where it
came up but it has not dominated at all. But nevertheless for
some people that's like the idea of fasting on יום כיפור, Yom
Kippur, you hurt your body and that's how much it atones, you're
slapping yourself and that somehow is you've punished yourself and that atones
for your sin. But okay, so there is an idea that is
around, but to this degree and you know, it's very hard... like
it does seem like he is blaming himself for something that might
not have been his fault, number one, and number two, he is
so racked with guilt and the extreme to which he's taking it
out. You know, I have a very hard time relating to this
as something to learn from other than learn from as a counter-example,
but I don't think that's what the גמרא Gemara, is intending.
Yes, I think that's right. Nonetheless, what about the word המתן? hamten?
Oh wait, interesting. So what could he have said?
Yes. Oh yes. Oh that's interesting. He started by saying yes rather
than wait a minute. Because wait is like a pushing off rather
than a pulling in.
I think actually if you go back and you read the contrast
to what we just said before about ארפכסד... Arpachshad... no, actually he
said ארפונא... Arpona... about ארפונא's Arpona interventions. ארפונא Arpona acts I think
are stories about limitations on intervention in the free economy. Except when
you have a situation where it's a medicine or somebody where there's
a dire need where safety makes the medicine available.
And he was being proactive
in this way.
Here this guy's traveling with a lot of food. Right and he
says wait a minute let me see what I can do for
you as opposed to saying yes let me help.
Ah nice point. It's a very good point.
It helps to emphasize that.
Yeah but it's a good point, it's a good point. Look I
think that we could say there was something he could have done
better or maybe you should have expected, you're traveling with all this
food, there are poor people around, maybe you should have had food
readily available when poor people come to you. Okay, so I think
there could be... you could find some area and I think it's
a very excellent point that he could have said yes rather than
wait. But still seems way over the top you know.
But the point is not about poor people, the point is about
people in dire straits and starvation, in an extraordinary circumstance. Right. Because
I think these set of stories really are a critique of international
aid.
We're not supposed to displace and simply go feed the hungry. We're
supposed to... that's the...
interesting, interesting. But I do think you're right in terms of like
the person that was going out with the gold chair, you know,
and he was going out and proactively looking what he could do.
Here you're traveling, you're being sort of very absorbed in your personal
world, you're going to your father-in-law, you're not sort of thinking about
yourself in terms of you're laden with food, you know, why aren't
you going out and also thinking, hey maybe I'll use the opportunity
to distribute some food. to people that I see along the way?
So again, if you wanted to read some type of a contrast,
but it's just a different cultural situation.
No, I understand that issue.
I don't see the גמרא Gemara necessarily emphasizing that point about the,
you know, but in terms of like what he could have been
doing a little bit different. He could have been going out not
absorbed in his personal world. He could have been going out like
the other rabbi who went out to look what he could do
in the commu- like in the society and maybe there's some of
that element there.
Jonathan, you thought this kind of emphasizes that he was so close
and the encounter was on the way, the source says on the
way and
right, and and maybe he's saying wait until I unload the donkey
meaning like not here, come see me in the office.
Oh, yeah,
when I get to—
oh, wait until I unload it when I get to my final
destination. Oh, that makes a lot of sense where the therefore that—
like that that's the real problem. Oh, oh, okay, that's very interesting.
I didn't read it that way, but if you read it that
way, then you really do understand why he's feeling very guilty. Like
if he said wait until I get to my destination and unpack
my bags, that's a big deal. Exactly,
exactly. Come see me in the
office, right. That's a— that's a very nice read. Jonathan, I think
I skipped you before. You had wanted to say— alright, alright. Okay,
so the מעשה maiseh says like this.
Okay, אמאי קרו ליה נחום איש גם זו? Amai karu lei Nachum
Ish Gamzu? So now we get to the stories of נחום איש
גם זו. Nachum Ish Gamzu. Why was he called נחום איש גם
זו? Nachum Ish Gamzu? דכל מילתא דהוה סלקא ליה אמר גם זו
לטובה. Dechol milta dehavah salka lei amar gam zu letovah.
Anything that would happen to him he would say even this is
for the best, which is impressive again just holding that up to
the previous story. Let's take a look at what the story is.
זימנא חדא בעו לשדורי ישראל דורון לבי קיסר. Zimna chada bau leshadurei
Yisrael doron levei keisar. One time, the Jewish people wanted to send
a gift to the Caesar's house. אמרו מן ייזיל ייזיל נחום איש
גם זו. Amru man yeizil yezil Nachum Ish Gamzu. Let נחום איש
גם זו Nachum Ish Gamzu go. דמלומד בניסין. Demelumad benissin.
He is accustomed to having miracles take— occur to him. Now, by
the way, one miracle that did occur to him you'll notice is
that his prayers of what should happen to his body were fulfilled.
We never exactly find out how that happened, but because he did
not presumably cut off his own arms, so, you know, we're all
talking about other people, right, חוני המעגל, Choni Hama'agel, other people whose
God listens to their prayers. So alright, for better or worse. Anyway,
presumably they knew that this was— I don't know if this is
before or after this terrible state had happened to him. But anyway,
presumably they knew that things— miracles would happen to him. שדרו בידיה
מלא סיפתא דאבנין טבן ומרגליות. Shadru bideih malei sifta de'avnin tavan umargaliyot.
They sent in his hands a full crate of precious jewels and—
and, you know, and stones. אזל בת בההוא דירא. Azal bat behahu
dira. He went and he slept in a certain lodging at night.
בההוא דירא. Behahu dira. בליליא קמו הנך דיראי ושקלינהו לסיפתא. Beleilya kamu
hanach daryei veshaklinhu lesifta. Night,
the other inhabitants got up and they took everything that was in
his box. ומלונהו עפרא. Umalunhu afra. And they put instead of it
dust, dirt. כי מטא התם. Ki mata hatam. When he got to
the Caesar's house. שרינהו לסיפתא. Sareinhu lesifta. They opened up the crate,
the box. חזיו דמלו עפרא. Chazyu demalu afra. They saw it was
filled with dust. בעא מלכא למקטלינהו לכולהו. Ba'ah malka lemaktalinhu lekulhu. The
king wanted to kill נחום איש גם זו Nachum Ish Gamzu and
the whole retinue. אמר קמחייכי בי יהודאי. Amar kamachaychi bi Yehuda'ei.
The Jews are mocking me. אמר גם זו לטובה. Amar gam zu
letovah. This will be for the best. אתא אליהו. Ata Eliyahu. So
אליהו הנביא Eliyahu Hanavi came. Once he— you know, maybe אליהו Eliyahu
was waiting to see how נחום Nachum would handle it, but now
that he saw that נחום Nachum had like faith that it would
always work out for the best, אליהו Eliyahu came. אידמי ליה כחד
מינייהו. Idmi lei kechad mineihu. And he appeared like one of them.
רש"י Rashi says them means one of the Caesar's retinue. ואמר ליה.
Ve'amar lei. דילמא האי עפרא מעפרא דאברהם אבוהון. Dilma hai afra me'afra
de'Avraham avuhon.
Because here you hear their father. That maybe this is the dust
from אברהם Avraham, their forefather. דכי הוה שדי עפרא הוי סייפי. Dechi
havah shadi afra havah sayyifei. When he would throw dust,
it would turn to swords. וגילא הוי גירי. Vegila havah girei. And
when he would throw straw, it would turn to arrows. דכתיב יתן
כעפר חרבו כקש נדף קשתו. Dechtiv yiten ke'afar charbo kekash nidaf kashto.
פסוק Pasuk in ישעיהו Yeshayahu that, you know, מי העיר ממזרח? Mi
he'ir mimizrach?
Who is it that was bestirred from the east? Right? So understood
to be referring to אברהם, Avraham, that the dust be— you know,
his dust is like his swords and the straw is like his
bow. So, you know, maybe this is the magical dust of אברהם
אבינו, Avraham Avinu, the dirt of אברהם אבינו Avraham Avinu that turns
into swords. הוי חדא מדינתא דלא מצו למיכבשה. Havah chada medinta dela
matzu lemichbasha.
So there was a certain country that they were— that they had
not yet been able to conquer. בדקו מיניה וכבשוה. Badku mineih vechavshuha.
So they tested out this dirt against this country. They threw dirt,
I guess, over the walls. And they were able to subdue it,
because it all turned into swords and it killed them all. עיילוהו
לבי גנזיה. Ayiluhu levei ganzeih. So anyway, it was magic dust and
it and it was— helped them conquer this country. עיילוהו לבי גנזיה.
Ayiluhu levei ganzeih. So they took נחום איש גם זו Nachum Ish
Gamzu and his retinue into their treasure houses. ומלוהו לסיפתיה אבנין טבן
ומרגליות. Umaluhu lesifteih avnin tavan umargaliyot.
And they filled his crate with all precious jewels. The same thing
that he had come to give them, they now gave him. ושדרוהו
ביקרא רבא. Veshadruhu beyikra raba. And they sent him out with great
honor. כי אתו בתו בההוא. Ki atu batu behahu. ביייסו בהו דירא.
bayisu behu dira. By the way, you know, it's interesting to mention
of אברהם, Avraham right? Goes down and gets sent out with all
of this wealth, right אברהם Avraham goes down to מצרים, Mitzrayim, gets
sent out. Again, I don't know if that's intentional, but there's obviously
some parallels there. Anyway, and אברהם Avraham when it says אברהם came
back, he says he came back and he's dwelled in the places
that he dwelled on his way down. Anyway, okay. When he came
back, he went and he slept back in the same lodging, בייסו
בהו דירא. bayisu behu dira. אמרו ליה amru leh they said to
him, מאי אתית בהדך דעבדי לך יקרא כולי האי? mai ayis behadach
deavdi lach yikra kulei hai? What did you bring to the Caesar
that he gave you such honor? They knew what they had brought,
they filled it with dirt, but what is it that you brought
to the Caesar that he gave you such honor? אמר להו amar
lehu he said to them, מאי דשקלי מהכא אמטי להתם, mai deshakli
mehacha amti lahatam, whatever I took out in my box here when
I left in the morning, that's what I brought there. סתרו לדירייהו,
setaru ledireihu,
so they figured if the dirt of their inn was so precious
to the Caesar, they knocked down their entire inn
ואמטינו לבי מלכא veamtinu levei malka and they brought it to the
Caesar's house. אמרו ליה amru leh they said to him, האי עפרא
דאייתי הכא מן דידן הוא. hai afra dayti hacha min didan hu.
That dirt that נחום איש גם זו Nahum Ish Gamzu brought to
you, that was our dirt. בדקוהו, badkuhu, so they tested the dirt
that these guys had brought ולא אשכחוה vela ashkachuh
and it wasn't magical. וקטלינהו להנהו דירייה, vkatlinhu lehanhu darya, so they
all got killed. Okay, so it was all for the best, they
all got killed and it all worked out for the best. Okay,
anyway, again, don't exactly know what to make of the story other
than the lesson of גם זו לטובה, gam zu letova, but I
do also want to say about the גם זו לטובה gam zu
letova idea that you know, there's, there could be a downside, but
it's great to have you know, faith for yourself that it'll all
work out for the best, but it could also lead for, you
know, lack of taking responsibility about what actually is happening, you know,
in practice. You know, like I sometimes talk about that in contrast
to, you know, like the יוסף Yosef and יהודה. Yehuda. You know,
יוסף Yosef is the one that says, you know, God will work
it out, God works it out for the best and whatever, you
know, and יהודה Yehuda is the one that steps forward and takes
responsibility. So,
so if it is meant some contrast with נחום Nahum here going
and taking, you know, his laden donkeys to his father-in-law's house, you
know, as opposed to whoever it was back there, רב הונא Rav
Huna that would go out and take responsibility for what's going on
in the community. If your attitude is everything God does, it'll all
work out for the best, you know, that could lead to, okay,
there are poor people around, there's sickness around, there's bad things, but
you know, it's all going to be for the best. Right? It
could lead to a real detachment from responsibility to what's happening. What?
He didn't guard his jewels, right, he didn't take certain steps. So
all these stories are very nice in taking the message that bad
things that happen, you should have בטחון, bitachon, you should have faith,
but to have that as your entire approach, right, can be lead
to, A, not taking responsibility for yourself and B, not taking full,
let's say, responsibility for the larger... Look, maybe that's part of the
story about the עני. ani. Maybe he didn't feel enough of a
sense of responsibility. If you have just a sense that everything God
is, is part of God's plan, you know, maybe you're not taking
enough responsibility yourself. Again, I don't know if the גמרא Gemara is
intending any of that critique, but that's what I'm, but that's what
I'm putting forward. Okay, let's keep on going. איזו דבר? eizu dever?
Now, what is this case of, you know, of pestilence that is
a reason to fast and for some of the neighboring villages to
participate in some way? עיר המוציאה חמש מאות רגלי, ir hamotzia chamesh
meot ragli, a city that has 500 foot soldiers, whatever that means,
and three people die over three days. תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan. עיר
המוציאה חמש מאות ואלף רגלי, ir hamotzia chamesh meot veelef ragli, if
a city has 1,500 foot soldiers כגון כפר עכו, kegon kfar Akko,
like Akko.
It's funny that Akko here, which is a big city apparently because
it has 1,500, but it's called a כפר kfar village, I don't
know about that. Anyway, ויצאו הימנה תשעה מתים בשלושה ימים veyatzu himena
tisha metim bishlosha yamim and nine people die over three days זה
אחר זה zeh achar zeh one after the other, הרי זה דבר,
harei zeh dever, then that is pestilence. ביום אחד או בארבעה ימים
אין זה דבר. beyom echad o bearbaa yamim ein ze dever. If
it's all in one day, you might think it's worse, but maybe
it's just some, you know, not a persistent thing and it's just
a freak chance. And if it's over four days, then maybe it's
not severe enough and that is not considered pestilence. Now, what's interesting
is, is that the גמרא, you know, interesting, whatever, the גמרא did
the math right, meaning, you could have said, if it's for 500
people, it's three people over three days, so for 1,500 people, you
know, somebody could have said, I mean, it would be wrong, well,
nine people over nine days. But no, because that's the exact same
as three people over three days. So maybe it's not such a
חידוש, chiddush, but people have been known to make that mistake. So
the point is it's still nine people, three people a day over
three days. Okay. עיר המוציאה חמש מאות רגלי. ir hamotzia chamesh meot
ragli. Now, a city that only has 500 people כגון כפר עמיקו
kegon kfar Amiku ויצאו ממנה שלושה מתים בשלושה ימים veyatzu mimena shlosha
metim bishlosha yamim זה אחר זה, zeh achar zeh, same point, three
people over three days, הרי זה דבר, harei zeh dever, then that
is דבר. dever.
ביום אחד beyom echad in one day או בארבעה ימים o bearbaa
yamim or in four days, אין זה דבר. ein zeh dever. It's
not. Again, even though it's all compressed, it's not דבר dever because
it's not as, necessarily, persistent.
דרוקרת Drokrat עיר המוציאה חמש מאות רגלי הוי. ir hamotzia chamesh meot
ragli havei. So דרוקרת Drokrat was a city of that had 500,
you know, again, soldiers, I don't know if it literally means soldiers
or, you know,
500. well
able-bodied men, whatever it means. ויצאו ממנה שלוש מתים ביום אחד, V'yatzeu
mimenu shalosh meisim b'yom echad, and three deaths occurred all in one
day. גזר רב נחמן בר רב חסדא תעניתא. Gazar Rav Nachman bar
Rav Chisda tanisa. רב נחמן בר רב חסדא Rav Nachman bar Rav
Chisda thought that this was דבר dever and he made a fast
day. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, so
רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak said to him, כמאן
כרבי מאיר? K'man k'Rabbi Meir? Who are you going like, that you
say three in one day is the same as three in three
days? That's like רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, דאמר, d'amar, who says by
a case of a goring ox, you know, what makes an ox
considered to be a מועד, muad, a habitual gorer? So the general
ruling is he gored one person a day over three days. You
know, so three people over three days. But what if he gored
three people in one day? So the first opinion is he's not
a habitual gorer. Maybe today he got crazy, but he's not a
habitual gorer. To which רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says, דאמר ריחק נגיחותיו
חייב, d'amar rikhak negichosov chayav, if when he spreads out the goring
you're liable for full because he's habitual, so קירב נגיחותיו לא כל
שכן? kirev negichosov lo kol sheken? If he compresses them, how much
more so is he a more violent or dangerous ox? But again,
it might be more intense, but it doesn't necessarily mean that it's
more persistent or habitual. So that was anyway, but that was
רב נחמן בר רב חסדא Rav Nachman bar Rav Chisda's approach and
he felt that three in one day is actually worse than three
in three days and made a תענית. taanis. Now that we have
רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak saying, you know, sort
of pushing back on רב נחמן בר רב חסדא, Rav Nachman bar
Rav Chisda, we're going to have one or two stories about that.
אמר ליה רב נחמן בר רב חסדא לרב נחמן בר יצחק, Amar
lei Rav Nachman bar Rav Chisda l'Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, so רב
נחמן בר רב חסדא Rav Nachman bar Rav Chisda said to רב
נחמן בר יצחק, Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, ליתי מר לגבן. Leisay mar
l'gaban. You know, you should move here, move to our place. Apparently
his place of רב נחמן בר רב חסדא Rav Nachman bar Rav
Chisda was a more place of תורה,
and you know, what are you doing in that small little village
there? Nobody, they don't really know תורה there. Come move to us,
to our place. אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said to him, תנינא.
Tanina. No, I teach a ברייתא. braisa. רבי יוסי אומר לא מקומו
של אדם מכבדו אלא אדם מכבד את מקומו. Rabbi Yosi omer lo
mekomo shel adam mechabdo ela adam mechabed es mekomo.
A person's place doesn't give him honor, the person gives honor to
his place. שכן מצינו בהר סיני. Sheken matzinu b'Har Sinai. We found
in הר סיני Har Sinai שכל זמן שהשכינה שרויה עליו, shekol zman
shehashchina shruya alav, as long as the Divine Presence was on הר
סיני, Har Sinai, אמרה תורה גם הצאן והבקר אל ירעו אל מול
ההר ההוא. amra Torah gam hatzon v'habakar al yiru el mul hahar
hahu. The animals couldn't graze. נסתלקה שכינה הימנו, Nistalka shchina heimenu, when
the שכינה shchina was lifted up from it, אמרה תורה במשך היובל
המה יעלו בהר. amra Torah bimshoch hayovel heimah yaalu v'har. Then the
mountain lost any significance and people could go up. So it wasn't
that the mountain was what was important, it was God's presence that
was important. וכן מצינו באהל מועד שבמדבר, V'chen matzinu b'Ohel Moed shebamidbar,
similarly in the אהל מועד Ohel Moed in the desert, שכל זמן
שהוא נטוי, shekol zman shehu natuy, אמרה תורה, amra Torah,
while it was spread, the תורה says וישלחו מן המחנה כל צרוע,
v'yishalchu min hamachaneh kol tzarua, and God's presence was there.
Let all of the, or maybe it means the place that the
אהל מועד Ohel Moed was, the אהל מועד Ohel Moed gave significance
to the place and all טמא tamei people had to be sent
away. הוקפלו היריעות, Hukplu hayerios, once the curtains were rolled up and
the אהל מועד Ohel Moed was dismantled, then that actual geographic space
was not itself significant. הותרו זבין ומצורעין ליכנס שם, Hutru zavin u'metzorain
l'ikanes sham, then all the טמא tamei people could enter into the
space. So thank you very much, I'm happy here. My presence gives
honor to the place, I don't need a place to give honor
to me. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so he said to him, אי
הכי ניתי מר לגבי מר. I hachi neisay mar l'gavei mar. So
you know what? If that's true, I should move over to where
you are, which is a little funny because I don't understand, you
know, it's like what's the joke? You know, the person who heard
that most accidents occur within five miles of home, so he moved.
So said, oh well if your presence honors the place I should
move you. Well what about your presence is honoring your place? But
maybe he felt that, you know, he was the more חשוב chashuv
person, like he was
the person of greater stature. So he says, alright, if that's true
and maybe he just wanted the company. So he said, if that's
true, if you're not moving to me, I should move to you.
So he said,
okay, אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said to him, no, מוטב יבא
מנה בן פרס אצל מנה בן מנה. Mutav yavo maneh ben pras
eitzel maneh ben maneh. It's appropriate for your initial request was more
appropriate because you were asking a hundred dollars, or you know the
son of fifty dollars, you know to come to a מנה maneh
the son of a hundred. ואל יבא מנה בן מנה אצל מנה
בן פרס. V'al yavo maneh ben maneh eitzel maneh ben pras. But
a hundred the son of a hundred shouldn't come to a hundred
the son of fifty, or a full the son of a half.
What does it mean? Because one was רב נחמן בר רב חסדא.
Rav Nachman bar Rav Chisda. So רב נחמן Rav Nachman's father was
a רב, whereas it was רב נחמן בר יצחק, Rav Nachman bar
Yitzchak, the one who is the one in the place that's saying
I'm not going to move, a person honors his place, his father
wasn't a רב. So he said no, no, no, you, you know,
I shouldn't come to you, you are from a more חשוב chashuv
heritage, you shouldn't be moving your place towards my place. Which one
does wonder you know a little bit like you know it seems
a little bit that רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak
was the more חשוב chashuv one and he was so you know
it's you know it's interesting exactly what this dynamic is whether he
really held that רב נחמן בר רב חסדא Rav Nachman bar Rav
Chisda was more חשוב chashuv in himself or he was just saying
his חשיבות chashivus came from his father. So but don't you move.
So but don't you move to me. Okay. בסורא הוה דברתא. Besura
hava de-barta. Okay so that was the end of that story. Let's
just I guess read one more story. בסורא הוה דברתא Besura hava
de-varta בשיבבותיה דרב. be-shivuvoteih de-Rav. In Sura there was דבר, dever, pestilence,
in the neighborhood of... in the... there was pestilence in Sura, בשיבבותיה
דרב לא הוה. be-shivuvoteih de-Rav lo hava. But it didn't afflict Rav's
little neighborhood. לא הוה דברתא. Lo hava de-varta. It didn't come into
Rav's neighborhood. סברו מינה, Savru minah, the people thought that משום זכותיה
דרב, mishum zechuteih de-Rav, that it was Rav's merit that saved them,
דנפיש, de-nafish, that it was so great that it saved them. Again
sort of like the merit of saving from the falling wall, here
the merit of a great rabbi or a great man saves from
the, from the דבר. dever. But now look, here again it's again
like a pushback on some of those earlier stories. So אתחזי להו
בחלמא, itchazi lehu be-chalma, the people who were saying this, there a
dream came to them and they saw in a dream that the
following
message. רב נפישא זכותיה טובא. Rav nafisha zechuteih tuva. Rav has much
merit. הא מילתא זוטרא ליה לרב. Ha milta zutra lei le-Rav. This
matter is too minor for it to be based on Rav's זכות.
zechus Rav's זכות zechus is so great, this doesn't need Rav's זכות
to save. I mean I don't know, דבר dever seems to be
a pretty, a pretty big thing, אלא משום ההוא גברא דשייל מרא.
ela mishum hahu gavra de-shayel mara. This all came on the merit
of a certain person, an unnamed person, that would lend out מרא
וזבילא mara ve-zavila like a shovel and a some other digging instrument,
לקבורה likvura to help people for burial. So because of his merit
that he would help people for burial when something came that would
kill people, his merit of helping people at moment of death was
enough to save that neighborhood. The
small anonymous the small deeds of anonymous people. And let's just read
one more story just like that.
בדרוקרת Be-Drokert which we heard about before הוה דליקתא, hava delikta, a
fire broke out. ובשיבבותיה דרב הונא לא הוה דליקתא U-be-shivuvoteih de-Rav Huna
lo hava delikta and it didn't break out in Rav Huna's neighborhood.
סברו מינה Savru minah בזכותא דרב הונא דנפיש. bizchuta de-Rav Huna de-nafish.
It's because of Rav Huna's merit which is so great. אתחזי להו
בחלמא Itchazi lehu be-chalma they saw in a dream, האי זוטרא ליה
לרב הונא. hai zutra lei le-Rav Huna. This would be too small
of a deal for Rav Huna. For Rav Huna's merit. You don't
need Rav Huna's merit for this. אלא משום ההיא איתתא Ela mishum
hahi iteta a certain woman דמחממת תנורא de-mechamema tanura that once she
would heat up her oven, fire up her oven, ומשיילא לשיבבותיה u-meshayela
le-shivuvoteih she'd let her neighbors use her oven that had already been
heated up and the fuel had already been used and it was
already hot, come and use my oven or else it's going to
waste, why waste your own fuel? So that was enough to save.
So again I think that this is like a beautiful counterpoint. We're
not denying the idea that great rabbis have great merits and that
will save them from great things, but in a way all we
heard about before was it saves them from falling buildings. Here if
you ask me, saving by stopping a fire and stopping pestilence is
at least as big of a deal although the גמרא's making it
more minor and I think there's a real power within what this
story that like the small little good deeds of anonymous
people can have a tremendous type of a saving effect. Okay so
end it at that. Yes.